Guide to the Hodder and Stoughton records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Hodder and Stoughton Records,
1875-1914
Hodder and Stoughton.
3 linear ft. (963 items in 6 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0598
7468840
History
English publishing firm, founded in the late 19th century.
Scope and Content
Correspondence and publishing agreements for many of their authors in the pre-World War I period.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 3 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Cataloged Contracts and Receipts
Series III: Uncataloged Correspondence and Documents
Subjects
Century Company.; Charles Scribner's Sons.; Aspden, Hartley.; Baillie-Saunders, Margaret Elsie Crowther, 1873-1949.; Barrie, J. M. (James Matthew), 1860-1937.; Barron, Percy.; Baum, L. Frank (Lyman Frank), 1856-1919.; Bayly, Elisabeth Boyd.; Beet, Joseph Agar, 1840-1924.; Bell, Charles Frederic Moberly, 1847-1911.; Bell, David Charles, 1817-1901.; Bell, J. J. (John Joy), 1871-1934.; Beresford, Max.; Best, S. F. Reynolds.; Boyd, Mary Stuart.; Brangwyn, Frank, Sir, 1867-1956.; Brontèe, Charlotte, 1816-1855.; Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861.; Bullen, Frank Thomas, 1857-1915.; Burnett, Frances Hodgson, 1849-1924.; Burnside, Helen Marion.; Cable, George Washington, 1844-1925.; Cahan, Abraham, 1860-1951.; Caine, Hall, Sir, 1853-1931.; Caine, Ralph Hall, 1869-1939.; Cairns, D. S. (David Smith), 1862-1946.; Campbell, Frances V.; Carey, Rosa Nouchette, 1840-1909.; Castle, Agnes, d. 1922.; Castle, Egerton, 1858-1920.; Cholmondeley, Mary, 1859-1925.; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965.; Combe, Theodora Williamson.; Connor, Ralph, 1860-1937.; Duncan, Sara Jeannette, 1861-1922.; Cowper, William, 1731-1800.; Crockett, S. R. (Samuel Rutherford), 1860-1914.; Crowther, Samuel, 1806?-1891.; Cullum, Ridgwell, 1867-; Cupples, George, Mrs., 1839-1898.; Dale, Alfred William Winterslow, Sir, 1855-1926.; Dawson, William James, 1854-1928.; Doudney, Sarah, 1843-1926.; Downey, D.; Downey, W.; Dudeney, Henry, Mrs., b. 1866.; Duncan, Norman, 1871-1916.; Engel, Georg, 1866-1931.; Everett-Green, Evelyn, 1856-1932.; Fairbairn, A. M. (Andrew Martin), 1838-1912.; Felkin, Alfred Laurence, b1856.; Findlay, Jessie Patrick.; Forrester Scott, G.; Fowler, Ellen Thorneycroft, 1860-1929.; Francis, Beata, d1899.; Frowde, Henry, 1841-1927.; Godfrey, Elizabeth.; Gorrie, Alfred E.; Gray, Maxwell, d. 1923.; Griffith-Jones, E. (Ebenezer), 1860-1942.; Gunn, Jeannie, 1870-1961.; Hammerton, John Alexander, Sir, 1871-1949.; Harley, Fannie Eden.; Harraden, Beatrice, 1864-1936.; Henderson, Robert, b. 1842.; Hinkson, H. A. (Henry Albert), 1865-1919.; Hitchcock, Ripley, 1857-1918.; Hocking, Joseph, 1860-1937.; Hocking, Silas K. (Silas Kitto), 1850-1935.; Hodder, Edwin, 1837-1904.; Hodder-Williams, J. E. (John Ernest), 1876-1927.; Holland, Clive, 1866-1959.; Hughes, Katherine Price.; Hutcheson, John C. (John Conroy); Hutton, Susan Katharine.; Jameson, E. M. (Elaine Mary); Johnson, A. E. (Alfred Edwin), b. 1879.; Kingsley, Florence Morse, 1859-1937.; Kingston, William Henry Giles, 1814-1880.; Kipling, Rudyard, 1865-1936.; Knight, George Halley, 1835-1917.; Lamb, Ruth, b. 1829.; Lawrence, Lady, b. 1878.; Lee, Elizabeth.; Lee-Hamilton, Eugene Jacob 1845-1907.; Liefde, J. B. de (Jacob B.), 1847-1878.; Lloyd, Nelson, 1873-1933.; Longridge, C. Nepean (Charles Nepean); Low, Will Hicok, 1853-1932.; Lowndes, Arthur, 1858-1917.; Lucy, Henry W. (Henry William), Sir, 1845-1924.; McCarthy, Justin H. (Justin Huntly), 1860-1936.; Macdonald, Greville, 1856-1944.; Macdonald, James Alexander b. 1862.; Maclaren, Ian, 1850-1907.; MacLean, Donald Findlay, 1874-1937.; Maclean, Norman, 1869-1952.; Macnaughtan, S. (Sarah), d. 1916.; Macquoid, Katharine S. (Katharine Sarah), 1824-1917.; Macquoid, Thomas Robert, 1820-1912.; Macrae, John, 1866-1944.; Malet, Lucas, 1852-1931.; Mann, Robert G.; Masson, Flora.; Masson, Rosaline Orme.; Matz, B. W. (Bertram Waldrom), 1865-1925.; Maxwell, W. B. (William Babington), 1866-1938.; Meade, L. T., 1854-1914.; Merrick, Leonard, 1864-1939.; Moffatt, James, 1870-1944.; Moody-Stuart, Charles.; Moody-Stuart, Kenneth, 1841-1904.; Moore, Frank Frankfort, 1855-1931.; Morgan, Kewpie.; Newnes, George, 1851-1910.; Nicoll, W. Robertson (William Robertson), Sir, 1851-1923.; Oman, John, 1860-1939.; O'Reilly, Robert,--Mrs.; Orr, James, 1844-1913.; Oxenham, John, 1852-1941.; Oxley, James Macdonald, 1855-1907.; Page, Jesse.; Parker, Gilbert, 1862-1932.; Paull, M. A. (Mary Anna), b. 1838.; Pegram, Fred.; Pennell, Joseph, 1857-1926.; Penrose, H. H., Mrs., 1860-; Quiller-Couch, Arthur Thomas, Sir, 1863-1944.; Raven-Hill, L. (Leonard), 1867-1942.; Raymond, Walter, 1852-1931.; Read, Opie Percival, 1852-1939.; Reaney, Isabel Edis, 1847-; Reed, Talbot Baines, 1852-1893.; Reynolds, Amy Dora.; Rice, Alice Caldwell Hegan, 1870-1942.; Rice, Cale Young, 1872-1943.; Ridge, W. Pett (William Pett), d. 1930.; Roberts, Henry Chalmers, 1870-; Robinson, W. Heath (William Heath), 1872-1944.; Rose, Charles E.; Rowlands, Effie Adelaide, 1866-1936.; Scott, Frank Hall, 1848-1912.; Scribner, Charles, 1854-1930.; Sergeant, Adeline, 1851-1904.; Shaw, Adele Marie.; Shorter, Clement King, 1857-1926.; Shorter, Dora Sigerson, 1866-1918.; Simpson, Evelyn Blantyre, 1856-1920.; Simpson, P. Carnegie (Patrick Carnegie), 1865-1947.; Skene, Felicia, 1821-1899.; Smith, David, 1866-1932.; Speight, E. E. (Ernest Edwin); Spurgeon, C. H. (Charles Haddon), 1834-1892.; Strahan, Geoffrey.; Steuart, John A. (John Alexander), 1861-1932.; Stevenson, Robert Louis, 1850-1894.; Stoddart, Jane T.; Stretton, Hesba, 1832-1911.; Swan, Annie S., 1859-1943.; Tauchnitz, Bernhard, 1816-1895.; Thayer, William Makepeace, 1820-1898.; Treeton, Ernest Adolphus.; Tynan, Katharine, 1861-1931.; Vachell, Horace Annesley, 1861-1955.; Vaizey, George de Horne, Mrs., b. 1857.; Vaizey, Harriet Reynolds.; Vernáede, R. E. (Robert Ernest), 1875-1917.; Waghorne, Arthur.; Ward, A. E.; Watt, A. P. (Alexander Pollock), 1834-1914.; Watt, Lauchlan MacLean, 1867-1957.; Weber, Allahna.; Wedmore, Frederick, Sir, 1844-1921.; Weyman, Stanley John, 1855-1928.; Whale, Winifred Stephens.; Whyte, Christina Gowans.; Wilson, David.; Wright, Thomas, 1859-1936.; Wright, William, 1837-1899.; Young, Egerton Ryerson, 1840-1909.; Young, Robert.; Authors and publishers.; Books--Translations.; Clergy as authors.; Copyright--England.; English literature--19th century.; English literature--20th century.; Literature publishing--England.; Publishers and publishing--England.; Translations.; Accounts.; Agreements.; Certificates.; Contracts.; Copyright certificates.; Financial records.; Legal instruments.; Lists.; Memorandums.; Receipts.; Artists' representatives.; Authors, American.; Authors, English.; Biographers.; Clergy.; Journalists.; Literary agents.; Novelists.; Poets.; Publishers.; Woman authors, American.; Woman authors, English.; Women biographers.; Women novelists.; Women poets.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Aspden, Hartley (Box 1-4)
  - Barrie, Sir James Matthew, 1860-1937
  - Barron, Percy
  - Bayly, Elizabeth Boyd
  - Bedford, Jessie ("Elizabeth Godfrey")
  - Beet, Joseph Agar, 1840-1924
  - Bell, Charles Frederic Moberly, 1847-1911
  - Bell, David Charles, 1817-1901
  - Bell, John Joy, 1871-1934
  - Bullen, Frank Thomas, 1857-1915
  - Cairns, David Smith, 1862-1946
  - Carey, Rosa Nouchette, 1840-1909
  - Dale, Sir Alfred William Winterslow, 1855-1926
  - Doudney, Sarah, 1843-1926
  - Downey, W. & D.
  - Duncan, Norman, 1871-1916
  - Fairbairn, Andrew Martin, 1838-1912
  - Findlay, Jessie Patrick
  - Fowler, Ellen Thorneycroft, 1860-1929
  - Frowde, Henry, 1841-1927
  - Gordon, Charles William, 1860-1937 ("Ralph Connor")
  - Gorrie, Alfred E.
  - Griffith-Jones, Ebenezer, 1860-1942
  - Hammerton, Sir John Alexander, 1871-1949
  - Henderson, Robert, 1842-
  - Hitchcock, Ripley, 1857-1918
  - Hocking, Joseph, 1860-1937
  - Hodder, Edwin, 1837-1904
  - Hughes, Mary Katherine Howard Barrett (Mrs Hugh P.)
  - Hutton, Susan Katharine
  - Kingston, William Henry Giles, 1814-1880
  - Knight, George Halley, 1835-1917
  - Lamb, Ruth Buck, 1829-
  - Lee, Elizabeth
  - Lucy, Sir Henry William, 1845-1924
  - MacDonald, Greville, 1856-1944
  - MacLean, Donald Findlay, 1874-1937
  - Macquoid, Katharine Sarah, 1824-1917
  - Macquoid, Thomas Robert, 1820-1912
  - Macrae, John, 1866-1944
  - Mann, Robert G.
  - Masson, Flora
  - Meade, L.T., 1854-1914 (Elizabeth Thomasina Meade Toulmin Smith)
  - Moody-Stuart, Kenneth, 1841-1904
  - Nicoll, Sir William Robertson, 1851-1923
  - Oman, John Wood, 1860-1939
  - Orr, James, 1844-1913
  - Oxenham, John, 1852-1941
  - Page, Jesse
  - Paull, Mary Anna, 1838- (Mrs John Ripley)
  - Pegram, Fred, 1870-
  - Pennell, Joseph, 1857-1926
  - Reaney, Isabel Edis (Mrs G.S.), 1847-
  - Reed, Talbot Bains, 1852-1893
  - Rice, Alice Caldwell Hegan, 1870-1942
  - Rice, Cale Young, 1872-1943
  - Scribner, Charles, 1854-1930
  - Sergeant, Adeline, 1851-1904
  - Shorter, Clement King, 1857-1926
  - Simpson, Evelyn Blantyre, 1856-1920
  - Simpson, Patrick Carnegie, 1865-1947
  - Smith, David, 1866-1932
  - Speight, Ernest Edwin
  - Steuart, John Alexander, 1861-1932
  - Stoddart, Jane T.
  - Strahan, Geoffrey
  - Stretton, Hesba, 1832-1911
  - Swan, Annie Shepherd, 1859-1943 ("David Lyall") (Mrs James Burnett Smith)
  - Thayer, William Makepeace, 1820-1898
  - Tynan, Katharine, 1861-1931
  - Waghorne, Arthur
  - Ward, Miss A.E.
  - Watson, John, 1850-1907 ("Ian Maclaren")
  - Weber, Allahna
  - Wedmore, Sir Frederick, 1844-1921
  - Young, Robert
- Series II: Cataloged Contracts and Receipts
  - Albanesi, Effie Adelaide Maria Henderson, 1859-1936 ("E.A. Rowlands") (Box 1-4)
  - Baillie-Saunders, Margaret Elsie Crowther (Mrs Frederick), 1873-
  - Barron, Percy
  - Bell, John Joy, 1871-1934
  - Bell, John Keble, 1875- ("Keble Howard")
  - Boyd, Mary Stuart Kirkwood (Mrs Alexander S.)
  - Brangwyn, Sir Frank, 1867-1956
  - Bullen, Frank Thomas, 1857-1915
  - Cable, George Washington, 1844-1925
  - Caine, Sir Hall, 1853-1931
  - Campbell, Frances V. Dean-Morgan (Mrs Howard D.)
  - Carey, Rosa Nouchette, 1840-1909
  - Castle, Egerton, 1858-1920 & Agnes Sweetman Castle, d.1922
  - Cholmondeley, Mary, 1859-1925
  - Combe, Theodore Williamson (Mrs Kenneth)
  - Cotes, Sarah Jeannette Duncan (Mrs Everard), 1861-1922 ("Jane Wintergreen")
  - Crockett, Samuel Rutherford, 1860-1914
  - Dawson, William James, 1854-1928
  - Doudney, Sarah, 1843-1926
  - Dudeney, Alice L. (Mrs Henry E.), 1866-
  - Duncan, Norman, 1871-1916
  - Engel, Georg, 1866-1931
  - Everett-Green, Evelyn, 1856-1932
  - Felkin, Alfred Laurence, 1856- ("A. St. Laurence")
  - Findlay, Jessie Patrick
  - Forrester Scott, G.
  - Fowler, Ellen Thorneycroft, 1869-1929
  - Francis, Beata, d.1899
  - Gordon, Charles William, 1860-1937 ("Ralph Connor")
  - Gunn, Jeannie Taylor (Mrs Aeneas), 1870-1961
  - Hammerton, Sir John Alexander, 1871-1949
  - Harley, Fannie Eden (Fannie Eden)
  - Harraden, Beatrice, 1864-1936
  - Hocking, Joseph, 1860-1937
  - Hocking, Silas Kitto, 1850-1935
  - Hodder, Edwin, 1837-1904
  - Holdsworth, Annie E. (Mrs Eugene J. Lee-Hamilton) ("Max Beresford")
  - Holland, Clive, 1866-1959 (Charles James Hankinson)
  - Hutcheson, John Conray
  - Hutton, Susan Katharine
  - Jones, Elaine Mary ("E.M. Jameson")
  - Kingsley, Florence Morse, 1859-1937
  - Kingston, William Henry Giles, 1814-1880
  - Kipling, Rudyard, 1865-1936
  - Lawrence, Jane Rosamond Napier, Lady, 1878- (Rosamond Napier)
  - Liefde, Jacob B. de, 1847-1878
  - McCarthy, Justin Huntly, 1860-1936
  - MacDonald, Greville, 1856-1944
  - Macdonald, James Alexander, 1862-
  - MacLean, Donald Findlay, 1874-1937
  - Maclean, Norman, 1869-1952
  - Macnaughtan, Sarah, d.1916
  - Macquoid, Katharine Sarah, 1824-1917
  - Masson, Rosaline Orme
  - Matz, Bertram Waldrom, 1865-1925
  - Maxwell, William Babington, 1866-1938
  - Meade, L.T., 1854-1914 (Elizabeth Thomasina Meade Toulmin Smith)
  - Merrick, Leonard, 1864-1939
  - Moffatt, James, 1870-1944
  - Moody-Stuart, Charles
  - Moore, Frank Frankfort, 1855-1931
  - O'Reilly, Eleanor Grace (Mrs Robert)
  - Oxenham, John, 1852-1941
  - Oxley, James Macdonald, 1855-1907
  - Page, Jesse
  - Parker, Sir Gilbert, 1862-1932
  - Paull, Mary Anna, 183338- (Mrs John Ripley)
  - Penrose, Mary Lewis (Mrs H.H.), 1860-
  - Quiller-Couch, Sir Arthur Thomas, 1863-1944
  - Raymond, Walter, 1852-1931 ("Tom Cobbleigh")
  - Reynolds, Amy Dora (Mrs Fred)
  - Reaney, Isabel Edis (Mrs G.S.), 1847-
  - Rice, Alice Caldwell Hegan, 1870-1942
  - Ridge, William Pett, d.1930 ("William Pettridge"; "Warwick Simpson")
  - Robinson, William Heath, 1872-1944
  - Rose, Charles E.
  - Séguin, Lisbeth Gooch, d.1890 (Mrs Alexander Strahan)
  - Sergeant, Adeline, 1851-1904
  - Sheldon, Charles Monroe, 1857-1946
  - Shorter, Clement King, 1857-1926
  - Shorter, Dora Sigerson, 1866-1918
  - Speight, Ernest Edwin
  - Steuart, John Alexander, 1861-1932
  - Swan, Annie Shepherd, 1859-1943 ("David Lyall") (Mrs James Burnett Smith)
  - Thayer, William Makepeace, 1820-1898
  - Treeton, Ernest Adolphus
  - Tuttiett, Mary Gleed, d.1923 ("Maxwell Gray")
  - Tynan, Katharine, 1861-1931
  - Vachell, Horace Annesley, 1861-1955
  - Vaizey, Harriet Reynolds & S.F. Reynolds Best
  - Vaizey, Jessie Bell (Mrs George de Horne), 1857-
  - Vernède, Robert Ernest, 1875-1917
  - Waghorne, Arthur & David Wilson
  - Watson, John, 1850-1907 ("Ian Maclaren")
  - Watt, Lauchlan MacLean, 1867-1957
  - Wedmore, Sir Frederick, 1844-1921
  - Weyman, Stanley John, 1855-1928
  - Whale, Winifred Stephens
  - Whyte, Christina Gowans
  - Wright, Thomas, 1859-1936
  - Wright, William, 1837-1899
  - Young, Egerton Ryerson, 1840-1909
- Series III: Uncataloged Correspondence and Documents
  - Albanesi, Effie Adelaide Maria Henderson, 1859-1936 ("E.A. Rowlands") (Box 5)
  - Baillie-Saunders, Margaret Elsie Crowther (Mrs Frederick),1873-1949
  - Baker, Mrs Louis
  - Barlow, Jane, 1857?-1917
  - Baum, L. Frank, 1856-1919
  - Bell, John Joy, 1871-1934
  - Bell, John Keble, 1875- ("Keble Howard")
  - Browning, Elizabeth Barrett, 1806-1861
  - Bullen, Frank Thomas, 1857-1915
  - Burnett, Frances Hodgson, 1849-1924
  - Carey, Rosa Nouchette, 1840-1909
  - Combe, Theodora Williamson (Mrs Kenneth)
  - Cooke, W.M.
  - Cotes, Sarah Jeannette Duncan (Mrs Everard), 1861-1922 ("Jane Wintergreen")
  - Crockett, Samuel Rutherford, 1860-1914
  - Cupples, Ann Jane Dunn Douglas (Mrs George), 1839-1898
  - Dawson, William James, 1854-1928
  - Dudeney, Alice L. (Mrs Henry E.), 1866-
  - Duncan, Norman, 1871-1916
  - Engel, Georg, 1866-1931
  - Everett-Green, Evelyn, 1856-1932
  - Felkin, Alfred Laurence, 1856- ("A. St. Laurence")
  - Fowler, Ellen Thorneycroft, 1860-1929
  - Francis, Beata, d.1899
  - Gordon, Charles William, 1860-1937 ("Ralph Connor")
  - Gunn, Jeannie Taylor (Mrs Aeneas), 1870-1961
  - Harrison, Mary St. Leger Kingsley (Mrs William), 1852-1931 ("Lucas Malet")
  - Holdsworth, Annie E. (Mrs Eugene J. Lee-Hamilton) ("Max Beresford")
  - Kingston, William Henry Giles, 1814-1880
  - Lawrence, Jane Rosamond Napier, Lady, 1878- (Rosamond Napier)
  - Lloyd, Nelson McAllister, 1873-1933
  - Low, Will Hicok, 1853-1932
  - Lowndes, Arthur, 1858-1917 (A.L.)
  - McCarthy, Justin Huntly, 1860-1936 (Box 6)
  - MacDonald, Greville, 1856-1944
  - MacLean, Donald Findlay, 1874-1937
  - Masson, Flora
  - Meade, L.T. (Elizabeth Thomasina Meade Toulmin Smith), 1854-1914
  - Merrick, Leonard, 1864-1939
  - Moody-Stuart, Charles
  - Moore, Frank Frankfort, 1855-1931
  - Morgan, Horace
  - O'Reilly, Eleanor Grace (Mrs Robert)
  - Oxenham, John, 1852-1941
  - Quiller-Couch, Sir Arthur Thomas, 1863-1944
  - Raymond, Walter, 1852-1931 ("Tom Cobbleigh")
  - Read, Opie Percival, 1852-1939
  - Reaney, Isabel Edis (Mrs G.S.), 1847-
  - Ridge, William Pett, d.1930 ("William Pettridge"; "Warwick Simpson")
  - Shaw, Adele Marie
  - Sheldon, Charles Monroe, 1857-1946
  - Shorter, Clement King, 1857-1926
  - Skene, Felicia Mary Frances, 1821-1899
  - Swan, Annie Shepherd, 1859-1943 ("David Lyall") (Mrs James Burnett Smith)
  - Tynan, Katharine, 1861-1931
  - Vachell, Horace Annesley, 1861-1955
  - Watt, Lauchlan MacLean, 1867-1957
  - Watson, John, 1850-1907 ("Ian Maclaren")
  - Weyman, Stanley John, 1855-1928
  - Young, Egerton Ryerson, 1840-1909
  - Misc. correspondence